בוקר טוב *Boker tov*. Today's דף daf. *daf* is ח' *Chet*. We
pick up at the very bottom of ז' עמוד ב' *Zayin amud
bet*. We're going through a list of statements about how powerful the
day, a day of rain is: גדול יום הגשמים *Gadol yom hageshamim*,
with related digressions.
And then we pick up with תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל *Tanna de-bei
Rabbi Ishmael*. It is about twelve lines from the bottom, line starts
with the word מצוה ותורה אור *mitzvah ve-torah or*, and the middle
of that line.
So, תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל *Tanna de-bei Rabbi Ishmael*: we taught in
the school of Rabbi Ishmael, אפילו בשעה שרקיע נעשה בהורין בהורין להוריד
טל ומטר *afilu besha'ah sherakia na'aseh bahurin bahurin lehorid tal u-matar*. So,
this is based on the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* we quoted yesterday which
was ועתה לא Lo ראו אור בהיר הוא בשחקים ורוח עברה ותטהרם
*ve-attah lo ra-u or bahir hu bash'hakim veruach avrah vatetaharem*. So even
at a time when the heavens appear to be like splotches, meaning
like there's dark clouds,
and it looks like it's ready to come to rain, to pour
down rain, nevertheless, ורוח עברה ותטהרם *veruach avrah vatetaharem*. It says this
is if a wind will pass and will cleanse it away. And
this is going back on the statement that we made yesterday which
is, I'm sorry, I probably should have started a little bit earlier,
but anyway the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, let's start from that פסוק
pasuk *pasuk*. I apologize. Let's go two lines above the line where
the הגהות הב"ח *Hagahot Habach*, the circle at the end, where it
says like this,
one minute,
I'm sorry, I'm just trying to reorient myself here.
Anyway, so, okay, no you know what, we'll continue. I'm sorry, we'll
continue. So anyway, so the point is that even that this is
saying that the rain is withheld because of the problem of ביטול
תורה bitul Torah. *bittul Torah*. And based on this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
of ורוח עברה ותטהרם *veruach avrah vatetaharem*, that a wind will come
and blow away the clouds even if it was ready to rain
because of the sin of ביטול תורה Torah, *bittul Torah*. אמר רבי
אמי Amar Rabbi Ami, *Amar Rabbi Ami*, this is probably where we
should have started. So the line starts with the word אמר רבי
אמי Amar Rabi Ami. *Amar Rabbi Ami*, about ten lines from the
bottom. אמר רבי אמי Amar Rabi Ami *Amar Rabbi Ami*: אין גשמים
נעצרין אלא בעוון גזל Gezel? *ein geshamim ne'etzarin ella ba'avon gezel*. So
that was based on an interpretation of an earlier verse and saying
that rain is withheld because of ביטול תורה Torah *bittul Torah*. Now
we are saying, and again, interesting to like, it's really a catalog
of what we have on the one hand is like a catalog
of ways in which a day of rain is praised and things
that it's similar to, and we also have a catalog of sins
and reasons why it won't rain.
And it's interesting to explore whether these are just attempts to try
to explain why it's not raining so you look for some type
of a causal explanation even within a context of sin and punishment,
or if there's other some type of a logical or religious symbolic
correspondence. So the idea of ביטול תורה Torah *bittul Torah* I think
I mentioned at the end of yesterday, the degree that rain is
not just the issue of providing sustenance but that rain is sort
of seen as a manifestation of God's closeness to the people, connection
to the people, and so on. So תורה Torah *Torah* is seen
as like the parallel, the way the people, תורה Torah, *Torah* and
תפילה Tefilla, *tfillah*, and we'll obviously get to תפילה Tefilla, *tfillah* again
and we've seen it before, is the way in which the people
express their relationship to God. So that sort of correspondence ביטול תורה
Torah *bittul Torah* and no rain makes a lot of sense. Here
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is now introducing another idea: אמר רבי אמי
Amar Rabi Ami, אין גשמים נעצרין אלא בעוון גזל Gezel *Amar Rabbi
Ami ein geshamim ne'etzarin ella ba'avon gezel* because of גזל Gezel? *gezel*,
because of stealing. שנאמר Shene'emar, על כפיים כיסה אור *Shene'emar al kapayim
kissa or*, so because on the palms the אור *or*, the light
is hidden, בעוון כפיים *ba'avon kapayim* because of the sin of the
hand, stealing something, taking something that isn't yours, כיסה אור *kissa or*.
ואין כפיים אלא חמס *Ve-ein kapayim ella chamas*, חמס כפיים *chamas kapayim*
means like theft, coveting, שנאמר she-ne'emar, ומן החמס אשר בכפיהם *shene'emar u-min
hachamas asher bechapayhem*. ואין אור אלא מטר *Ve-ein or ella matar*, and
light is rain, which is interesting, שנאמר she'ne'emar, יפיץ ענן אורו *shene'emar
yafitz anan oro*, the cloud will spread shine forth its light. So
here it says a result of גזל Gezel *gezel*. מאי תקנתיה mai
takantei, *Mai takantei*? What is the way to fix it? ירבה בתפילה
*Yarbeh bitfillah*, שנאמר she'ne'emar, ויצו עליה במפגיע *shene'emar vayetzav aleha bamafgi'a*, and
command on him with במפגיע *bamafgi'a*. ואין פגיעה אלא תפילה Tefilla, *Ve-ein
pegi'ah ella tfillah*, encountering is only תפילה tfilah. *tfillah* prayer, שנאמר she'ne'emar,
ואתה אל תתפלל בעד העם הזה ואל תשא בעדם רינה ותפילה ואל
תפגע בי *shene'emar ve-attah al titpallel be-ad ha-am ha-zeh ve-al tissa ba-adam
rina u-tfillah ve-al tifga bi*, and do not encounter me. So again
the idea that it's connected to גזל Gezel, *gezel* makes a certain
amount of sense. We mentioned yesterday the idea that it was connected
to not giving of תרומות ומעשרות *trumot u-ma'asrot*, which is the rain
provides for the crops and then your acknowledgment of God's what God
has helped in terms of the crops is your giving of the
תרומות ומעשרות *trumot u-ma'asrot*. So if you withhold that, God's going to
withhold the rain. So that made sense. גזל *Gezel* in another way
as well, I think is, I would like to interpret it similarly,
that the idea is that God provides. If you're not, and if
you take something from somebody else, you're sort of not acknowledging sort
of the idea of God giving you and God giving others and
God is
providing. taking and taking the things that don't belong to you, then
God will withhold the rain, which is you know, which is what
God is giving to you. That gets withheld.
Yes, גזל, right? The first mention was תורה, Torah then then he
had תפילה, tfilah, and now it's uprooting גזל?
Maybe,
maybe. I don't know if I would call גזל an uprooting, but
maybe, maybe. But the interesting issue though I would also say though
is that the response is תפילה, right? You could have said what's
the response to גזל? It should be returning the money, response to
גזל should be תשובה. Teshuvah. Now of course to some degree they're
interpreting the verse here, but again I think that the idea, the
major theme of this מסכת Masechet is that rain is God's you
know, favor, God's presence, whatever, and the absence of rain is responded,
the response is fast, yes, but in addition to fast, prayer. And
in a way fast and prayer more than תשובה Teshuvah is the
emphasis of this מסכת, Masechet, and these are, we'll get to fast
when we get to it, but prayer certainly is our reaching out
to re-establish that connection and you know, so it's all about that
relationship. So it is interesting that even though the sin is a
sin of theft and there's a lot of ways in which you
correct גזל, the response to the holding back of the rain directly
is the issue of תפילה, yes.
Also I mean remember the difference elsewhere, right, that between גזילה Gezeilah
and
גניבה? Gneivah? Yes, גזילה Gezeilah you don't
fear people or God. Right, so here you're re-establishing, that's a nice
point.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara, says like this, okay, אמר רבי
אמי, מאי דכתיב, Mai dechtiv, what's meant by the verse, אם קהה
הברזל והוא לא פנים קלקל? Im kehah habarzel vehu lo fanim kilkel?
So if if the iron has been dulled and it not the
face has corrupted, whatever that means, so let's see what the גמרא
Gemara does with this. אם ראית רקיע שקהה כברזל, Im raita rakia
shekehah kabarzel,
if you see the the heavens are like as dull as iron
and it's not going to rain, probably also relating to the verse
right that says in the קללה Klalah that I will make your
I will make the skies like iron, מלהוריד טל ומטר, Milehorid tal
umatar, and
they that rain is not going to be coming from them, they're
as hard as iron. Why is that? בשביל מעשה הדור שהן מקולקלין,
Bishvil maaseh hador shehein mekulkallin,
it's because of the sin of the nation which is corrupt, שנאמר
והוא לא פנים קלקל. Shene'emar vehu lo fanim kilkel.
So it's not exactly clear how we read this verse, some want
to say that it's interpreting the לא lo למד אלף lamed-alef or
the לו Lo למד ויו. lamed-vav. You know, they the face of
them or the way they present themselves they have corrupted, the whole
nation has has sinned. So here actually is the statement, not connected
to any particular sin, but that the absence of rain, you know,
sort of like the פסוקים Psukim we say in the שמע, Shema,
you know, if you do the מצוות Mitzvot you get the rain,
if you don't do the מצוות Mitzvot you don't get the rain.
So the absence of rain means that the whole generation is sinning.
מה תקנתם? Mah takanatam? And now again interestingly, what is the way
you fix it? יתגברו ברחמים, Yitgabru berachamim,
so with compassion which means prayer, which so again it's not about
that the response is תשובה, Teshuvah, the response is prayer, שנאמר וחילים
יגבר ויתרון הכשר חכמה. Shene'emar vechayalim yigaber veyitron hachsher chochmah.
So what does that mean? חילים Chayalim is like the strength, power
what? יגבר. Yigaber. Okay, I was right the first time. So the,
you know, the power that they should strengthen, you know, their sort
of you know their outcry and ויתרון הכשר חכמה, Veyitron hachsher chochmah,
and what does it mean the end of it, ויתרון הכשר חכמה
כל שכן אם הכשירו מעשיהם מעיקרא. Veyitron hachsher chochmah kol shekein im
hichshiru maaseihem mei'ikara.
ויתרון, Veyitron, it would have been better, הכשר חכמה Hachsher chochmah they
would have been smart at the beginning and they would have corrected
their deeds and they wouldn't have sinned to begin with. But now
that they did sin and they're not getting the rain they should
call out to God. Again interesting, not תשובה, Teshuvah, call out to
God. Okay, so let's take a look. ריש לקיש אמר, Resh Lakish
amar, אם ראית תלמיד, Im raita talmid,
now we're going to shift the discussion as we did a little
bit before, moving sometimes between discussions of rain to תלמוד תורה. Talmud
Torah. Okay, אם ראית תלמיד שלימודו קשה עליו כברזל, Im raita talmid
shelimudo kasheh alav kabarzel, דף ח' עמוד
א', Daf chet amud aleph, if you hear see a student that
his, you know, his learning he's like like we say hitting his
head against the wall, it's as hard as iron, he's not getting
anywhere with his learning. Why is that? בשביל משנתו שאינה סדורה עליו,
Bishvil mishnato she'einah sdura alav, because he does not have his information
well organized, right? Because you know in an oral culture anyway you
had to first memorize all the information, have it all in your
head and then you could analyze. So if a person is having
a hard time sort of thinking through issues, doesn't have a clarity
of thought, isn't analyzing well, it's because he doesn't have the information
well organized in his head.
שנאמר, She-neemar, so the פסוק pasuk says, והוא לא פנים קלקל. Vehu
lo fanim kilkel. So the way רש"י Rashi would explain this, והוא
לא, Vehu lo, if he's not succeeding it's because פנים קלקל fanim
kilkel he's like, you know, he's corrupted or he's messed up the
face of things, the basic organization, his basic information is a mess.
So מה תקנתו? Mah takanto?
How do you fix this? ירבה בישיבה, Yirbeh bishivah, spend time, רש"י
Rashi says this doesn't just mean sitting, it means literally in a
ישיבה, Yeshiva, spend time
sitting. כנאמר וחיילים יגבר. v'chayalim yigaber. And
what amongst like the power, you know, with great power or fortitude
he will increase, so means so רש״י Rashi says that that means
that the students are like troops, are like חיילים chayalim and amongst,
you know, your interaction with the other ישיבה yeshiva students, you will
strengthen your knowledge. These what?
חיילות חיילות. chayalot chayalot. Right, חיילים. chayalim. What? The female says that's
חיילות. chayalot. Right. רש״י Rashi says חיילות חיילות. chayalot chayalot. במחנות במחנות.
b'machanot b'machanot. Okay. ויתרון הכשיר חכמה.
v'yitron
hichshir chachmah.
כל שכן אם משנתו סדורה עליו מעיקרא. kol shekein im mishnato sedurah
alav me'ikara. יתרון, yitron,
it would have been better, הכשיר חכמה, hichshir chachmah, his wisdom would
have been organized from the outset. It fits better with the word
חכמה chachmah here, the emphasis on תורה Torah, study as opposed to
before, the emphasis on rain. Okay. כי הא דריש לקיש, ki ha
d'Resh Lakish, like ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, now that we're talking about
this, let's talk about the importance of, you know, of doing חזרה
chazarah and getting all of your information down before you start thinking
it through. כי הא דריש לקיש הוה מסדר מתניתיה ארבעין זמנין. ki
ha d'Resh Lakish hava mesader matnitei arba'in zimnin. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
would organize his material, not only necessarily do חזרה, chazarah, but like,
you know, organize it in his head forty times כנגד מ״ם יום
שניתנה תורה, k'neged mem yom shenitnah Torah, opposite the forty days the
תורה Torah. was given. So, you know, you have to own the
תורה Torah. that you've received. There's an idea here again, there's two
stages, right? There's the receiving of the מסורה, mesorah, the receiving of
what's being passed down, the oral tradition, which is like also the
facts. Again, in an oral culture you don't have books, so all
the previous teachings and משניות. mishnayot. So there's this process of receiving
the תורה, Torah. and so he would spend forty days in terms
of owning that material and really having it well under, well organized.
ועייל לקמיה דרבי יוחנן, v'ayeil l'kamei d'Rabbi Yochanan, and then he would
apply his own intellect and analysis and go in front of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to learn and to and to think about it.
So first own the material before you start analyzing it. In a
way this evokes other discussions in the גמרא, Gemara like about סיני
ועוקר הרים. Sinai v'oker harim. Is it more important, you know, to
have to just like be like a, you know, like a library,
have a lot of erudition, know all the facts? Or is it
important to have power of analysis? And the גמרא Gemara there concludes,
you know, you can't do the analysis before you have the facts.
And here too it's a similar idea except it's not a question
necessarily just about like the importance
of, you know, of learning it first, but also of really making
sure it is well organized and understood and clear and then to
apply the analysis. 39 times? Exactly. So רב אדא בר אבא מסדר
מתניתיה עשרין וארבע זימנין. Rav Adda bar Abba mesader matnitei esrin v'arba
zimnin. Look,
I teach the דף. How much time you spend in the rest
of the day doing חזרה, chazarah, that is your responsibility. So רב
אדא בר
אבא מסדר מתניתיה עשרין וארבע זימנין, Rav Adda bar Abba mesader matnitei
esrin v'arba zimnin, twenty-four times כנגד תורה
נביאים וכתובים, k'neged Torah Nevi'im u'Khtuvim,
תנ״ך, Tanakh, there's twenty-four books of תנ״ך. Tanakh. ועייל לקמיה דרבא, v'ayeil
l'kamei d'Rava, and then went in front of רבא. Rava. And again
the correspondence here in both of these places about the תורה Torah
that you get from God, whether it's the forty days of מתן
תורה matan Torah or the twenty-four books of תנ״ך, Tanakh, and then
your own sort of thinking and analyzing, you know, almost with תורה
שבכתב, Torah shebichtav, תורה שבעל פה Torah shebe'al peh relationship, although here
it applies to תורה שבעל פה Torah shebe'al peh as well, but
the תורה שבעל פה Torah shebe'al peh that is received, you know,
the facts and the information that is received, like the forty days
of תורה Torah, or the twenty-four books of תנ״ך Tanakh and then
your analysis and your input. But you have to give the first
part enough time. We're all eager to make our חידושים, chiddushim, but
first you have to know the facts.
Oh, yeah, and with the twenty-four books of תנ״ך Tanakh that they're
written, so you don't
need this much time to memorize it. Right, once you're talking about
a written תורה, Torah, so you get it into the state that
it is as if it's written. Right, that's a good point too.
You have you own it so that it's, it's written as if
it's written in front of you and then once you get down
like that then you can start thinking and analyzing it. Okay. רבא
אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava said, אי חזית תלמיד שלימודו קשה עליו
כברזל, ei chazit talmid shelimudo kasheh alav k'varzel, going back to this
פסוק pasuk again about the iron, if you see a student that's
having a hard time with his with his studies, it's as hard
as iron for him, he can't get into it, he can't grab
it, so בשביל רבו, bishvil rabo, it is not his problem, he
didn't do enough חזרה, chazarah, it's his master's problem שאינו מסביר לו
פנים, she'eino masbir lo panim,
that he's not showing a face, you know, like a a friendly
face. Now you might think the word מסביר masbir here means like
he's not explaining it to him, but it's like סבר פנים יפות.
sever panim yafot. Right.
Oh, סבר, sever, לשון נופל על
לשון,
lashon nofel al
lashon, double layer.
Yeah, that could be, you know, that he's not explaining it well
and he's not a, he's not a welcoming presence. It could be
you're right. So להסביר לו, l'hasbir lo, he's not explaining to him,
it's right. That's a nice point. Maybe it is both. שנאמר והוא
לא פנים קלקל, shen'emar v'hu lo panim kilkel,
and again here maybe the לא is written with, is understood as
like a ו, vav, he is showing him like an unfavorable face.
And close to והוא קהה, v'hu keha, which he's not nourishing.
That's interesting too. That's interesting too. מאי תקנתיה, so how does, what's,
what's the fix for this? So interestingly he talks to the student,
not to the רב. Rav. rabbi here, דאייבלא רבייה de-ayvela rabbeih
try to you know make nice with your rabbi, have friends come
and try to you know cultivate, you know have have his friends
talk him, oh, you should be nice to this guy, he's a
good student, he's a good guy.
No, no, ירבה עליו רעים.
yearbeh alav rei'im. No, no, ירבה עליו רעים, yearbeh alav rei'im, meaning
so you try to get friends to, you know, to sort of
persuade him to have a more positive relationship. So שנאמר, ובחילים יגבר.
uv'chayalim yigaber. Is that how it, יגבר? yigaber?
And like troops, you know, or, you know, you shall increase or
strengthen, so have people like, you know, amass around him and, you
know, try to influence him. Overcome, right, overcome. ויתרון הכשיר חכמה. v'yitron
hachshir chochmah. כל שכן אם הוכשרו מעשיו לפני רבו מעיקרא. kol sheken
im huchshru ma'asav lifnei rabbo mei'ikara.
It doesn't get this guy off the hook, like obviously the master
isn't being just mean for nothing, so maybe this guy has done
something wrong. So, you know, it would have been better if he
wouldn't have demonstrated whatever character traits or whatever things made the master
not like you so much, you know, made the rebbe not like
you so much. But now that that's the reality, you know, sometimes
once you set somebody off, you know, it has a, you know,
it has a longer impact well disproportionate to whatever the original quote-unquote
like crime was. So, you know, it would have been better if
whatever that initial problem was it hadn't happened in the first place
that led to this situation. But now that we're in the situation,
you got, you know, you at least the talmid if you want
to make it better, don't just complain, figure out how you're going
to try to cultivate a more positive relationship. Okay, so now, so
now that's the end of that. Again, it's quite fascinating the regular
movement between the rain discussion and the Torah discussion, back and forth.
We've done it many, many times. And again, you know, sort of
the power of Torah as, you know, again what is sort of
a central concern in the time, you know, as opposed to certainly
as opposed to sort of the central concern and the central importance
of rain. Also that whole idea of the nurturing nature of the
Torah. Yes.
And even what you're really framing is rain conceptualizing rain as God's
presence, so the rain comes from God, comes to the earth. Right.
So what comes from human beings in response is language
in
two forms, prayer and Torah.
Right, so that we said, I know you might have not been
for that first minute, so that we definitely said, which is why
the גמרא Gemara yesterday ended with, you know, rain doesn't come because
of ביטול תורה. Torah. In a way, you know, we get from
God God's שפע, shefa, exactly, and what we sort of do to
create that relationship on our end is prayer and תורה. Torah? So
that's that way. But the, but the other thing that's happening here
is not that the Torah is our sort of
our response or our side of that relationship, but that the same
פסוקים pesukim that are that are brought to talk about, you know,
the blessing of rain and the things that how powerful rain is
or why rain isn't coming, there's a regular shift in the גמרא
Gemara that's happened more than once where it looks back at those
same פסוקים pesukim and interprets them in terms of תורה. Torah So
there's also, I think, the other side of that thing whereas the
Torah that is coming from God, which is also the spiritual sustenance
that we receive from God, and that type of a parallel.
Yes. Just things, one, I find interesting, the student who is talking
to rabbi here is בר אהבה. Bar Ahava.
Ah, that's interesting. Right.
And also this whole discussion about rain sort of in its time
or gentle rain and then rain that's, yeah, that's really harsh, that's
really, you know, destructive. And so here we also, yeah, it's maybe
the teacher is teaching but he's teaching in
a in a rain that's harsh. Right. So again, those are all
interesting parallels once we start recognizing exactly some of the way in
which the Torah here is being paralleled to the rain. Also, if
the rebbe here is God and giving the Torah in a certain
way, so what the student tries to improve the relationship, so God
is withholding the rain and we pray, you know, so there's a
lot of interesting things to think about what this parallel suggests. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
ואמר רבי אמי, v'amar Rabbi Ami, מאי דכתיב? mai de-chtiv? What's meant
by the verse, אם ישוך הנחש בלא
לחש? im yishoch hanachash belo lachash? Thank you, הנחש בלא לחש hanachash
belo lachash ואין יתרון לבעל הלשון. v'ein yitron l'ba'al halashon. If the
snake will will bite without a without the
without the hissing and there's no what is the then and there's
no benefit to the to the person of the tongue, to so
let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. אם ראית דור
שהשמים משתכשין כנחשת, im ra'ita dor she-hashamayim mishtachshin k'nechoshet,
if you see a generation in which the heavens are משתכשין, mishtachshin,
Rashi and Tosafot seem to say this means like ready, red or
rusted over like like bronze, מלהוריד טל ומטר mil'horid tal u'matar and
there's no rain coming out of it. So that's the ישוך, yishoch,
excuse me, ישוך, yashoch, excuse me, בשביל לוחשי לחישות. bishvil lochshei lachishot.
Now, if you would say לוחשי לחישות, lochshei lachishot, that doesn't normally
evoke very positive imagery, right, a לחש lachash like a little incantation
that you say over like, you know, over some type of a
wound in order to heal
it, or think about a serpent and a snake, you think about
לשון הרע, lashon hara, which we'll get to. But look what the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* initially does with it. בשביל לחשי לחישות *bishvil lachshei
lechishot*, those that do whisperings of their whisperings, שאין בדור *she'ein bador*,
that you don't have them, you don't have the people here going
back to your point that are doing the speaking that is necessary.
It's because of the absence of prayer. So as opposed to before
what was some sin, but prayer is the rectification, here the very
absence of rain starts because of the absence of prayer. And again
about that whole thing about that relationship of people to God. שאין
בדור *she'ein bador*. No, I do not, I do not think so.
מאי תקנתיה *mai takantei*? Yeah, what is the way to fix it?
מאי תקנתיה *mai takantei*, ילך אצל מי שיודע ללחש *yeilech eitzel mi
sheyodeia lelachash*. Go find somebody who knows how to pray. דכתיב *dechtiv*,
as the verse says, יגיד עליו רעו yagid alav re'o, *yagid alav
reio*. So this is again from the, from a different פסוק *pasuk*
actually. But it's a פסוק *pasuk* that's read in the context of
rain. His neighbor will speak about him. ואין יתרון לבעל הלשון v'ein
yitron l'ba'al halashon, *ve'ein yitron lebaal halashon*. Okay, so that's that. יגיד
עליו רעו yagid alav re'o, *yagid alav reio*. So that's that. So
if you can't pray, have somebody pray for you. יגיד עליו רעו
*yagid alav reio*, let your neighbor pray for you. By the way,
I think this is evoking the idea that we're going to see
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, that when it stops rain, there's this
special relationship in the משניות *Mishnayot* between the יחיד *yachid* and the
ציבור tzibur. *tzibbur*. When it doesn't rain initially, the יחידים *yechidim* begin
to fast, right?
And then after, and then still doesn't work, then the ציבור tzibur
*tzibbur* fasts as well. Then at the end, nothing is happening, so
at a certain point the ציבור tzibur *tzibbur* stops even trying to
fast and pray, but the יחידים *yechidim* continue to fast and pray.
So there's this whole role of the יחידים *yechidim* and the famous
whole stories of חוני המעגל *Choni HaMa'agel*, right? חוני *Choni* the circle
drawer and how he's able to get God to listen to him
and so on. So this special role of יחידים *yechidim* in prayer
is something that's also a theme of this מסכת *masechet*. And here
it's coming out. Your prayers aren't working. Find the יחיד *yachid* that
can do the praying. Find the people that can pray for you.
דכתיב *dechtiv*, יגיד עליו רעו *yagid alav reio*. ואין יתרון *ve'ein yitron*,
now we go back to the פסוק *pasuk*, ואין יתרון לבעל הלשון
*ve'ein yitron lebaal halashon*. So ומי שאפשר לו ללחוש ואינו לוחש *umi
she'efshar lo lilchosh ve'eino lochesh*. This is the פסוק *pasuk* in אם
ישוך הנחש בלא לחש *im yishoch hanachash belo lachash*. So you don't
have the ability to speak your, to speak yourself, and that's why
it's not raining. ואין יתרון לבעל הלשון *ve'ein yitron lebaal halashon*. ומי
שאפשר לו ללחוש ואינו לוחש *umi she'efshar lo lilchosh ve'eino lochesh*, מה
הנייה לו *mah hanayah lo*? So if there's what benefit is it
that you there are people that are ואין יתרון *ve'ein yitron*, there's
no benefit to a person of the tongue. If somebody has the
power of speech, so what good is he if he's not using
that power of speech? So what good are you if you're not
praying and you're able to pray and you could make a difference?
ואם לחש ולא נענה *ve'im lachash velo ne'enah*, and if you prayed
and you were not answered, and that by the way is a,
is also a theme, right? The whole idea is you start fasting
and the משנה mishna *Mishnah* said, התענו ולא נענו v'lo na'anu. *hitanu
velo ne'enu*, and they weren't answered and they weren't answered. It's a
regular theme of the משניות *Mishnayot* about what happens when you fast
and you're not answered. So you prayed and you weren't answered. So
what do you do? מאי תקנתיה *mai takantei*? Now what can you
do? ילך אצל חסיד שבדור ויעתר עליו בתפילה *yeilech eitzel chasid shebador
veyeitar alav bitfillah*.
So again, it's interesting, right? The first stage is just get somebody
who knows how to דאוון *daven*. Maybe it's not, maybe it's not
even talking about a highly righteous person, just somebody who, you know,
who maybe in an oral culture when again you didn't have written
סידורים *siddurim*, maybe you don't even know the תפילה *tefillah*. So stage
one is you get somebody who knows how to דאוון *daven*. That
doesn't work. Stage two is you get a real חסיד *chasid*. Again,
this idea of like the יחידים *yechidim*, the very special people, and
you get him to pray. שנאמר *shenemar*, ויצו עליו במפגיע *vayitzav alav
bemafgia*. Again, that's and אין פגיעה *ein pegiah*, and
we had the word פגיעה *pegiah* before, ואין פגיעה אלא תפילה *ve'ein
pegiah ella tefillah*. שנאמר *shenemar*, ואתה אל תתפלל בעד העם הזה ואל
תשא בעדם רנה ותפילה ואל תפגע בי *ve'ata al titpallel be'ad ha'am
hazeh ve'al tisa ba'adam rinah utfillah ve'al tifga bi*. Okay, so you
have somebody, a מפגיע *mafgia*, somebody who's able to entreat God and
encounter God and now you get somebody not only who knows how
to pray but who is in a very special status and hopefully
that'll make a difference. ואם לחש ועלתה בידו *ve'im lachash ve'altah beyado*.
Okay, so all of this, notice again, this is so much like
I think a distillation of the themes that were before, because before
prayer was a תקנה *takanah* for some other problem. Here's a whole
thing about rain and absence of rain or presence of rain is
all about prayer, you know, whether there's prayer and whether prayer is
being done well. Okay, now, ואם לחש ועלתה בידו *ve'im lachash ve'altah
beyado*,
let's say you did the prayer and you were successful. The opposite
of לא נענה *lo ne'enah*. Not and you were successful, it rained,
right? ומגיס דעתו עליו *umagis da'ato alav*, but now as a result
you're acting very haughty. Oh, look at this. Look how effective my
prayer was. And one again also wonders whether this is, you know,
alluding to the story of חוני המעגל *Choni HaMa'agel*, like because you
remember חוני המעגל *Choni HaMa'agel*, right? He's sort of always ordering God
around exactly how he wants it to rain. So let's say God
is responding and now you're feeling very, you know, very haughty about
the efficacy of your prayers. מביא אף לעולם *meivi af la'olam*. That
brings anger to the world. שנאמר *shenemar*, מקנה אף *mikneh af*. Now
עולה, olah one that acquires anger because of עולה avlah, going up.
So if you are מגיס דעתו עליו, magis da'ato alav, you're very
haughty, you know, and your sense of yourself rises up, then the
response will be anger. So you have to be on the one
hand the power, you know, your speech is so powerful in affecting
the, you know, the relationship with God, creating that relationship, bringing about
the rain, the absence of the rain, and at the same time,
you have to be very humble in that whole approach.
Is the פסוק על עולה al olah or על עולה? al avlah?
It might be עולה, olah but the גמרא Gemara I didn't, I
must say I didn't look at it, check it up, but the
גמרא Gemara is reading it עולה olah? because of עולה דעתו עליו.
oleh da'ato alav. Does it have the עולה? There you go. Okay.
רבא אמר, Rava amar,
רבא Rava says, I gotta tell you, I gotta say the quotes
איוב Iyov all over are like, they're like the Hebrew is harder
than the Aramaic. Alright, anyway. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says,
שני תלמידי חכמים שיושבים בעיר אחת, shenei talmidei chachamim sheyoshvim b'ir achat,
again,
notice, like, it's almost like, you know, like without even any transition,
we're talking about rain, we're talking about תורה. So שני תלמידי חכמים
שיושבים בעיר אחת ואין נוחין זה לזה בהלכה, shenei talmidei chachamim sheyoshvim
b'ir achat v'ein noachin zeh l'zeh b'halacha, if you have two תורה
scholars that are in the city and they're not pleasant one to
the other in הלכה, halacha, meaning מה שלא היה בהלכה, mah shelo
hayah b'halacha,
yeah exactly, right, so and now again why did it say הלכה
halacha not תורה, not exactly clear. Before also we got about maybe
echoing the discussion before about when it talks about sharpening one another
and you know, and working בחברותא b'chavruta and doing it בהלכה b'halacha
which maybe is the more, you know, I don't know, very nuanced
and technical aspect and maybe people also, you know, you know feels
a lot of sense of like weight because of the practical application.
Anyway it's interesting the word here הלכה halacha as opposed to תורה,
but nevertheless, maybe, but again, you know, people get angry. I פסקן
pasken this way, you're פסקן-ing pasken the other way. Maybe it's not
even as just as theoretical as תורה. So there's a lot of,
they're not, they don't share with one another, there's not good collaboration.
So if that's what's happening, מתקנאים באף, mitkana'im b'af, so they get,
you know, sort of it leads to them being jealousy with anger,
ומעלים אותו umalin oto and they sort of, you know, and it
rises up. Again רש״י Rashi has different ways of reading this but
it just like increases the anger. שנאמר, as the verse says, מקנה
אף על עולה. makne af al olah. So you acquire anger and
it does just continue to rise up. Now where, how does that
connect to the to the idea that they're not pleasant one another
with תורה? So because it is
the end of the פסוק of יגיד עליו רעו, right? It's יגיד
עליו רעו מקנה אף על עולה. yagid alav re'o makne af al
olah. So רש״י Rashi says you should be יגיד עליו רעו, you
should be, you know, talking to your neighbor and discussing things and
collaborating, and if not then it will just lead to an increase
in jealousy and anger. Okay. Okay, so in keeping going, so going
on, but again just to note the immediate shift from the rain
discussion to the תורה discussion. אמר ריש לקיש, amar Reish Lakish, ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish says, מאי דכתיב mai d'ichtiv אם ישוך הנחש בלא
לחש ואין יתרון לבעל הלשון? im yishoch hanachash belo lachash v'ein yitron
l'ba'al halashon? So back to this thing which before we talked about
rain and prayer. What's the meaning of this verse about the serpent
that bites without hissing? So לעתיד לבוא, le'atid lavo, in the future,
מתקבצים ובאים כל החיות אצל הנחש, mitkabtzim uva'im kol hachayot etzel hanachash,
famous גמרא, Gemara all of the animals will come around, will surround
the serpent, the snake, ואומרים לו, v'omrim lo, and say to them,
look, look, we understand other animals. ארי דורס ואוכל, ari dores v'ochel,
a lion sort of tramples, you know, sort of kills its prey
and then eats it. זאב טורף ואוכל, ze'ev toref v'ochel, the wolf
kills its prey and goes and eats it. אתה, atah, so we
understand they do violence to other animals, but it's for their own
sustenance, they eat the food that they kill. אתה מה הנאה יש
לך? atah mah hana'ah yesh lach? You, why do you go ahead
and
you know you kill a person? I mean the funny thing is
that normally a snake has poison and kills in order to eat,
but every now and then a snake will kill, I don't know,
a cow or a person and it won't exactly eat the thing
that it kills. So you, what benefit is there for you that
you go ahead and you kill and you don't eat from it?
אתה מה הנאה יש לך? atah mah hana'ah yesh lach? אמר להם,
amar lahem, so the snake will say back to
them, ואין יתרון לבעל הלשון, look, you can ask the same question
about somebody who tells לשון הרע. lashon hara. They go ahead and
with their words they can you know destroy people's reputation, literal like
kill people, and what benefit do they get? They don't get richer
from it, you know, they don't get any benefit from it, but
nevertheless as the point seems to be a little rhetorical, which is,
there is a type of הנאה hana'ah people get from you know
from using their speech to hurt other people, not necessarily a legitimate
הנאה, hana'ah, but you know, so it's not physical, but there's that
type of הנאה. hana'ah. So me too I get הנאה hana'ah from
killing people with my with you know with what when I bite
them. Okay so... אמר רבי אמי. So that was a very powerful
read of that verse. So but now we get back to our
discussion of praying. אמר רבי אמי אין תפילתו של אדם נשמעת אלא
אם כן משים נפשו בכפו. ein tfilato shel adam nishma'at ela im
kein masim nafsho b'kapo. Now that we're talking about prayer and prayer
as being central to the whole rain story, we're going to talk
about how your prayer is heard. So a prayer is only heard
only if you actually put your soul in your hands. שנאמר, meaning
you put you know you like expose yourself, your true self, and
you bring it to God. שנאמר, as the verse says נשא לבבנו
אל כפים אל אל בשמים. nisa levavenu el kapayim el El bashamayim.
Right, let us bring up lift up our hearts on our hands.
So if you really come with your heart in hand, right we
have that phrase nowadays, right heart in hand? Right, so anyway, then
your prayer will be answered. So the גמרא Gemara says איני, eini,
is that really true?
והאוקים שמואל אמורא עליה ודרש, v'hukim Shmuel amora alei v'darash, Shmuel put
an אמורא amora which is like somebody who like would announce his
teaching, you know proclaim it, and he and he expounded in the
following
way: ויפתוהו בפיהם, vayefatuhu befihem, they you know appeased him seduced him
talking about God with their mouth ובלשונם יכזבו לו, uvilshonam yekhazvu lo,
but with their tongues they lied to him meaning they you know
said things that weren't true, they ולבם לא נכון עמו, velibam lo
nakhon imo, and their hearts were not true you know with God,
were not faithful, meaning so they said their prayers, they said the
right words, but it wasn't sincere. ולא נאמנו בבריתו, velo neemnu bivrito,
and they were not faithful to the covenant. So does not so
seems like completely you know
objectionable, and nevertheless ואף על פי כן, v'af al pi khein, what
does the next verse say? והוא רחום יכפר עון, vehu rakhum yekhaper
avon, God will forgive sin. So even when the prayer is insincere.
So that's a very powerful idea, when would you ever imagine that
you would find in the גמרא Gemara an אמורא amora would say
that even if your prayer is insincere, God will listen to it.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not
difficult כאן ביחיד כאן בציבור. kan b'yakhid kan b'tzibur. It would depend
whether it's a person an individual or the community. The individual, it
has to be sincere, you have to bring your heart in hand.
The community, you just do the prayers and God will be responsive.
Now that's a very fascinating idea, but you know what I would
say is is that to the degree that we're talking here about
the whole idea of this issue of the relationship, right? So sometimes
it's like, you know, just having the communication even if it's not
coming from the depths of your heart and even if it's not
totally sincere, but the idea of just reaching out and being in
communication is a powerful thing of sustaining the relationship, right? Better to
have to be communicating than to talk than not to be talking.
But again, the power of the difference between that at the communal
level, you know, as opposed to at the individual level. This is
something that maybe, you know, there's some power to it when it's
done as the entire community is still reaching out to God even
if it's not so much about there's not so much sincerity behind
it, you know, there still is a power to that. So it
ties into other גמרות, Gemarot, you know, about אין תפילת של ציבור
חוזרת ריקם, ein tfilat shel tzibur khozeret reikam, you know, those types
of other statements about the power of דאוונינג בציבור. davening b'tzibur. But
I think there's a difference here because I think those types of
statements tend to reflect more like right like, you know, oh it's
powerful when you're with a ציבור. tzibur But this isn't just powerful.
This is like a completely different phenomenon. This is like a completely
like, you know, just
insincere prayer. So one could say it's not even תפילה. If your
words don't mean what you're feeling, right? The basic issue of תפילה,
עבודה שבלב. avodah she'balev. So it's one thing to say it's more
powerful in the context of the community; it's another thing to say
when it's actually just the recitation of words that are said insincerely.
So I do think there's a real power here and I do
think, as I said, it has something to do with not just
expressing your feelings and your emotions and your thoughts but that the
very act of speech is itself a sustaining of the relationship. Yes.
It seems like רש״י Rashi has
a simpler way of understanding it. It's almost as if it's בטל
בשישים, batel b'shishim, right? In other words, you have a whole ציבור
and the ציבור can absorb some of the individual insincerities that might
be within its midst because fundamentally the ציבור will be sincere.
You mean because רש״י Rashi says שאין לב כולם שלם. she'ein lev
kulam shalem. Exactly.
But you know
but then רש״י Rashi says I don't know do you read all
of them aren't but some of them are or or
all of them are insincere. שאין לבם she'ein libam the first. Yeah
I don't know because רש״י Rashi says רש״י Rashi says he points
out the plural language of ויפתוהו בפיהם ובלשונם יכזבו לו. vayefatuhu befihem
uvilshonam yekhazvu lo. It's all plural and talking about all of them
being insincere. I don't know, what you're saying is more understandable, it's
easier to but I think the גמרא Gemara is making a more
bold a bolder claim, right you know? So
okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבי אמי, אין
גשמים יורדים, ein gshamim yordim, now we get back to rain. Okay
again it's also interesting to explore why sometimes it says the rain
is only withheld because of X as opposed to this which is
in the more positive, the rain only falls because of Y. Okay.
So rain only comes, אין גשמים יורדים Ein geshamim yordim אלא בשביל
בעלי אמנה, Ella bishvil baalei amana, people that deal faithfully with one
another. Okay, it doesn't mean like people who believe in dogma, it
means people who deal faithfully in business with one
another. Trustworthy. As the verse says, אמת מארץ תצמח, Emet me-eretz tizmakh,
truth will sprout forth from the ground, וצדק משמים נשקף, ve-tzedek mishamayim
nishkaf, and justice from heaven looks down. But here צדק tzedek is
understood to be the rain, what comes from heaven if not the
rain? But that's in response to the truth that comes from the
earth. דאמר רבי אמי בא וראה, De-amar Rabbi Ami bo u-re-eh, and
Rabbi Ami says, come and see, כמה גדולים בעלי אמנה, kama gedolim
baalei amana, how great are people who deal
with faith, with good faith with one another. מנין, Minayin, where do
you see this from? מחולדה ובור, Me-chulda u-vor, from the weasel and
the hole and
the pit. ומה המאמין בחולדה ובור כך המאמין בהקדוש ברוך הוא על
אחת כמה וכמה, U-ma hamaamin be-chulda u-vor kakh hamaamin ba-Kadosh Barukh Hu
al akhat kama ve-khama, certainly how much more so somebody who believes
in God. So what is this talking about? Just shows you how
sometimes you need the right type of cultural context reference. רש״י Rashi
and תוספות Tosafot quote a מדרש midrash of a story that somebody
was... a young man and woman
fell in love and they made an oath
to not marry anybody else until the time that they were of
age to get married. And the young woman said to the man,
and who's going to
hold you to your oath? So he said, well, this weasel and
this well. And anyway, so many years passed and he didn't live
up to his promise and he married another woman and they had
two kids. And one kid fell down in the well and died
and the other kid was attacked by the weasel and died. And
his wife said to him, what's happening here? So he told her
the story. So she said, oh, you know what, you gotta keep
your oath. So he divorced his wife and he went and he
married the other young woman and it all ended happily ever after,
I
guess.
So that's... anyway, so
look, if you call the weasel and the well to hold you
to your thing and they will come to make sure you keep
your faith, how much more so if you hold God as your
witness. I don't know exactly what that's teaching, is it teaching you
the power of dealing faithfully or is it teaching you the consequences
of dealing in bad faith? But anyway, the idea is that if
you deal with one another in good faith, then God will respond
by bringing the rain. And again, bringing God into the equation, otherwise
again in these cases I ask what exactly is the correspondence? So
here the next statement helps you understand the correspondence. If the idea
of dealing with good faith is because you are implicitly or explicitly
holding God and saying as God is my witness or bringing God
into the equation, then that's bringing God as the partner, as a
presence
in your business dealings and very much into... so again gets back
to this issue of the relationship and therefore it's not only being
in good faith with your friend, but in good faith with God.
And therefore the response being the rain is completely appropriate. Okay, so
now the גמרא says like this: אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
כל המצדיק את עצמו מלמטה, kol hamatztik et atzmo milmata, מצדיקין עליו
את הדין מלמעלה. maztikin alav et hadin milmala. So since we did
if you do X below, then Y will happen above, we're into
this mode now. So anybody, המצדיק את עצמו מלמטה hamatztik atzmo milmata
sounds like a good thing, but the way רש״י Rashi reads it
is that it is a good thing, but in the following way:
that you try to act very scrupulously below, so מצדיקין עליו את
הדין מלמעלה. maztikin alav hadin milmala. Now you would think that means,
oh, so they'll be good with you above, but צידוק הדין, tzidduk
hadin, if you know, is not necessarily a good thing. It means
bad things happen, but it's all in the end, it's all just.
So רש״י Rashi says it means they'll be very exacting with you
from above, actually get punished for small oversteps, because this is the
idea that if somebody is a צדיק, tzadik, then you hold them
to a higher
standard. שנאמר, אמת מארץ תצמח וצדק משמים נשקף Emet me-eretz tizmakh ve-tzedek
mishamayim nishkaf again. So if you're truthful on the ground, then justice
comes from above. It's an accounting method.
Exactly, every line, you can't overlook
each dot.
רבי חייא בר אבין אמר רב הונא, Rabbi Chiya bar Abin amar
Rav Huna, מהכא דכתיב, me-hakha de-khaktiv, וכיראתך עברתך, u-kheyiratekha evratekha, like the
fear of You is Your anger. So again, ironically, the more fearful
somebody is of God and the more exacting they are, then they'll
get punished more for their sins, but again, in the end somehow
the accounting all works
out. ריש לקיש אמר מהכא, Reish Lakish amar me-hakha, פגעת את שש
ועשה צדק בדרכיך יזכרוך הן אתה קצפת ונחטא בהם
עולם ונושע. pagata et sas ve-oseh tzedek bidrakhekha yizkerukha hen atah katzaphta
va-nekheta ba-hem olam ve-nivasha. הן אתה קצפת ונחטא בהם עולם ונוושע *hen
atah katzaphta venecheta bahem olam venivashea*. You have been, become angered and
we have sinned through them and we will be, we will be,
what do you call it,
saved. So again, it's a very hard פסוק *pasuk* to unpack, but
the point is here's somebody that is doing צדק בדרכיך *tzedek bidrachecha*
and they are the same ones that you are פגעת *pagata*, that
you have smitten and that you have קצפת *katzaphta*, that you have
been angered at them. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי *Amar Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi*—ונוושע *venivashea*, thank you. Is it ונוושע *venivashea* or ונוושע *venivashea*?
ונוושע *venivashea*. ונוושע *venivashea*. Okay. So אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי *Amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*, says Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, כל השמח ביסורין
שבאין עליו *kol hasameach beyissurin sheba'in alav*, so now maybe this is
the proper follow-up to that because here we're saying that things, bad
things are happening to you and it's because you are being very
righteous. So he says if you rejoice in the afflictions that befall
you, מביא ישועה לעולם *meivi yeshua la'olam*, it brings salvation to the
world. שנאמר *shenemar*, בהם עולם ונוושע
*bahem olam venivashea*, through them, through ונחטא בהם *venecheta bahem* and קצפת
*katzaphta* your anger, we will be ultimately, it will bring salvation. Now
by the way, the other thing this functions, you know, you could
say well this is functioning to tell me don't try to be
such a צדיק *tzadik* and don't try to be so righteous because
then you'll get in trouble. But the other thing this helps for
is dealing with the reverse problem which is the צדיק ורע לו
*tzadik vera lo*. You look around you and you see these, you
know, righteous people and they're suffering and what's that about? Oh, let
me tell you, the explanation is that God is super exacting and
in the end it'll all work out in some divine accounting. Okay,
so and again, it's interesting once we're recognizing the problem of righteous
that are suffering, you know, that it all works out, you know,
but how does that work together with the whole theme of the
מסכת *masechet*, which is it's not raining and therefore we got to
do תשובה teshuva *teshuva*, and the תשובה *teshuva* or whatever will bring
the rain, but we know sometimes good people can be punished and
suffer and so on. But again, I do want to say that
part of the answer here I think is is that this מסכת
*masechet* is not really focused on תשובה *teshuva*. I mean there is
a little תשובה *teshuva* comes up in this מסכת *masechet*, but it's
focused on prayer and fast and not on תשובה *teshuva*. So it
might be true, it might be that, you know, that you could
be righteous and still be very, you know, and still suffer, but
nevertheless, you know, it's that there's this sense of the issue around
the rain has a lot more to do I would say with
like the relationship question than the question about exactly how righteous you
are or how sinful you are. One minute, the גמרא *Gemara* continues.
Okay, yeah, go ahead, what's your question?
Just the the answerable theological question in the end is like what
you're saying is why does הקדוש ברוך הוא *Hakadosh Baruch Hu* sometimes
exercise more דין din. *din* than רחמים *rachamim*? Yeah, right.
But my question is not, is not theological. My question is how
חז"ל *Chazal* are dealing with the phenomenon, right? And how do you
deal with the whole idea of it's not raining, let's pray, and
does that mean I have to buy into a, you know, to
a thoroughgoing שכר ועונש *sachar va'ones*, רשעים *rasha'im* suffer and צדיקים *tzadikim*
are rewarded in this world? What about all the contradictions to that
and what about the גמרא *Gemara* we just read? So what I'm
trying to say is I think that one of the things that
alleviates some of that problem is that the issue here about rain
is not merely all about
sin and, you know, versus, you know, and punishment. It's a much
more, I would say, it's about relationship than it is about sin
and punishment and therefore some of those questions are less severe. Obviously
the גמרא *Gemara* does raise various types of sins, but, you know,
it also speaks about, as we've said, the rectification being prayer, not
necessarily the focus on תשובה *teshuva*. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says
like this, אמר ריש לקיש מאי דכתיב mai de-chtiv? *Amar Reish Lakish
mai dichtig*, what's meant by the verse ועצרת השמים *ve'atzart hashamayim*, God
will close up the heavens, right? This is the פסוק *pasuk* about,
you know, reward and punishment based on rain, directly about you do
the מצוות *mitzvot*, it rains, you don't, you do the עבירות *aveirot*,
it doesn't rain. ועצרת השמים *ve'atzart hashamayim*, God will close up the
heavens. בשעה שהשמים נעצרין מלהוריד *besha'ah shehashamayim ne'etzarin milehorid*, when טל *tal*
or טלם *talum* or מטר *matar*, anyway, when the, when the heavens
are closed up from bringing rain, דומה לאשה שמחבלת ואינה יולדת *domeh
le'isha shemechabelet ve'eina yoledet*. It's like a woman that is undergoing child
pain and a birthing pain and cannot give birth. והיינו דאמר ריש
לקיש משום בר קפרא *vehainu de'amar Reish Lakish mishum Bar Kappara*. So
now if, now before we get to the next statement, so what's
the importance of this? So if you look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*,
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says שחובלת *shekovelet*, כמו חבלת *kemo chavlas*, רש"י Rashi
*Rashi*, כמו חבלי לידה *kemo chevlei leida*, אף השמים עושים כן וקשה
לעולם והחטא *af hashamayim osim ken vekasheh la'olam vehacheit*. So רש"י *Rashi*
gets us back to the חטא *cheit*. It's because of a sin
and it's hard for the world. But if anything, that would not
be the imagery that would come to my head. If the heavens
are trying and they're not succeeding, God is having a hard time
as it were giving birth. God wants to bring the rain, God
is in pain, right, and suffering and is not able to. And
in a way again, I say that this really speaks towards this
sense of God, you know, this desire for God to connect us
and have this relationship and the pains, pain that's in when it's
not able to actually succeed. I do not see חטא *cheit* as
being a scene here. I do not, רש"י *Rashi* is bringing that
back in. So now the גמרא *Gemara* goes on and says והיינו
דאמר ריש לקיש משום בר קפרא נאמרה עת *vehainu de'amar Reish Lakish
mishum Bar Kappara neemra at* עצירה בגשמים ונאמרה עצירה באשה. It says
to be held up by rain and to be closed up by
the woman. נאמרה עצירה באשה, Ne-emra atzira be-isha, שנאמר כי עצר עצר
ה' בעד כל רחם, she-ne-emar ki atzor atzar Hashem be-ad kol rechem,
God had closed up every womb, you know, by Avimelech. ונאמרה עצירה
בגשמים, Vene-emra atzira bigshamim, דכתיב ועצר את
השמים, de-chtiv ve-atzar et ha-shamayim,
the heavens will be closed up. נאמרה לידה באשה ונאמרה לידה בגשמים.
Ne-emra leida be-isha vene-emra leida bigshamim. So now we're getting before we
discussed rain as this very sort of male sexual imagery
penetrating the earth. Here we talk about the rain in sort of
the feminine, right? The giving birth. So it says birth by woman,
says birth by the rain. נאמרה לידה באשה, Ne-emra leida be-isha, דכתיב
ותהר ותלד בן. de-chtiv vatahar vateled ben.
Interesting, could have quoted a lot of פסוקים pesukim by לידה באשה.
leida be-isha. ונאמרה לידה בגשמים, Vene-emra leida bigshamim, דכתיב והולידה והצמיחה. de-chtiv
veholidah vehitzmichah.
Now it is a little bit of a trick here because it's
not really the feminine imagery, right? Because והולידה veholidah is הפעיל, Hif'il,
right? And this is the rain penetrates the earth and the earth
is והולידה. veholidah. So the earth is the mother earth, the earth
is the feminine, the rain isn't. So it's a little sort of
eliding some of these different
differences. Okay. נאמרה פקידה באשה ונאמרה פקידה בגשמים. Ne-emra pekida be-isha vene-emra
pekida bigshamim. נאמרה פקידה באשה, Ne-emra pekida be-isha, דכתיב וה' פקד את
שרה. de-chtiv v'Hashem pakad et Sarah. God remembered Sarah. ונאמרה פקידה בגשמים,
Vene-emra pekida bigshamim, דכתיב פקדת הארץ
ותשוקקה רבת תעשרנה פלג אלהים מלא מים. de-chtiv pakadta ha-aretz vateshoke-ke-ha rabat
taasherenah peleg Elokim malei mayim. You have remembered the earth and it
is become, you know, you have watered
it, you have much enriched it, the פלג אלהים peleg Elokim is
filled with water. So the stream of God filled with water. So
by the way, before we go on and unpack that verse, the
again notice who's being remembered here. Not the clouds, not the heavens,
but the who's being remembered? God you remembered what? הארץ, ha-aretz, the
earth. So if you've talked about the feminine imagery in both in
two out of the three verses, it's not the rain, it's the
earth. The earth is the mother earth that gets the rain and
then brings forth and is remembered and brings forth the child. So
again it's interesting the way the גמרא is, people get that? The
way the גמרא is sort of lumping that together, although really in
the פסוקים pesukim it is much more the rain being the masculine
and the earth being the feminine but the גמרא sort of brings
that all together. Okay, so מאי פלג אלהים מלא מים? mai peleg
Elokim malei mayim? תנא כמין קובה יש ברקיע. tana kemin kubba yesh
barakia. There's like a hut or like some type of a chamber
in the heavens שממנה גשמים יוצאים, she-mimmenah geshamim yotzim, that rain comes
from there. All right, whatever that means. אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני:
Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani: מאי דכתיב? But again, you know, רש"י
started this by the link to sin, I don't see sin here
mentioned at all, you know, and again I see this idea, again
this imagery, this very obviously, you know, fecund imagery of birthing and
the birth and birthing coming from heaven and even the פסוקים, pesukim,
you know, God or the birthing coming from the earth. Again talk
about the nature of the intimate relationship that's being sort of, you
know, sort of created here and the way the rain sort of
speaks about that relationship of God and heaven to earth is I
think very powerful. Okay,
so where
were we? אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני: Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani:
מאי דכתיב אם לשבט אם לארצו אם לחסד ימציאהו? mai de-chtiv im
leshevet im le-artzo im le-chesed yamtzi-ehu? If to the rod or to
the land or to kindness he will find it. What does that
mean? אם לשבט, Im leshevet, if the rains have been declared to
be for smiting, like they were going to be harsh rains, then
and the way רש"י means this, and then God had like a
people did תשובה or God had a change of heart, then בהרים
ובגבעות, beharim uvigva'ot, God will bring it down onto the mountains and
the and the valleys where it won't hurt people, you know, where
it'll sort of just, you know, do no harm. אם לחסד, Im
le-chesed, if it had been decreed that it would be a kind
rain, so ימציאהו לארצו, yamtzi-ehu le-artzo, God will bring it to the
land, and maybe his land, to ישראל, Yisrael, בשדות ובכרמים, bisadot uvekramim,
into the fields and the vineyards. Now we'll look at the פסוק
again. אם לשבט, Im leshevet, if it's a harsh rain, לאילנות, le-ilanot,
it should go to the trees. As we said before, harsh rains
are good for the trees. אם לארצו, Im le-artzo, so
if it's for the land, not for the trees, then לזרעים, lezra'im,
it'll go for like the type of rain that's appropriate for the
land. Not a harsh rain. Harsh rain was the trees. It's two,
three פסוקים, pesukim, שבט, shevet, ארצו, artzo, חסד. chesed. Sorry, okay. So
if it's לארצו, le-artzo, if it's meant for the land, לזרעים, lezra'im,
it'll go for the seeds and the plants. אם
לחסד, Im le-chesed, ימציאהו, yamtzi-ehu, if it's for kindness ימציאהו בראש שיחין
ומערות, yamtzi-ehu berosh sichin ume'arot, let it go and fill the well.
Okay, so I guess it means that it's a lot of rain.
So it's not and that the benefit of a lot of rain
will be to fill the wells. You don't want it flooding on
your land, you know, in your field, but it's good for the
wells. בימי רבי שמואל בר נחמני הוי כפנא ומותנא. Bimei Rabbi Shmuel
bar Nachmani hava kafna umotna. In the time of רבי שמואל בר
נחמני Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani there was two things: there was a
famine and there was a and there was a plague.
So כפנא *kafna* also like there was no rain and there was
a plague. אמרי היכי נעביד *Amri heichi na'avid*? The people said what
should we do? ניבעי רחמי אתרתי *Niba'ei rachmei a'tarti*? Should we pray
for both? לא אפשר *Lo efshar*. You can't pray for two things.
All right we'll see what that's about. אלא *Ella* but by the
way notice again the response here is prayer, right? In מסכת תענית
ta'anit *Masechet Ta'anit* the response to things is not תשובה *teshuvah*. The
response to things is prayer. Okay so should we pray? No you
can't pray for two. אלא ניבעי רחמי אמותנא *Ella niba'ei rachmei a'mosna*.
Look let's pray for the plague which is causing death to cease,
וכפנא נסבול *v'kafna nisbal* and we'll somehow manage with the famine, at
least we'll be alive. אמר להו רבי שמואל בר נחמני *Amlei Rabbi
Shmuel bar Nachmani* so שמואל בר נחמני *Shmuel bar Nachmani* said back
to them: No. ניבעי רחמי אכפנא *Niba'ei rachmei a'kafna*. We're going to
pray for the famine, for the lack of rain, for the drought,
דכי יהב רחמנא שובעא לחיי הוא דיהיב *de'chi yav rachmana sova l'chayei
hu d'yahiv*, because when God gives plenty, He gives it to bring
about life. God will not, sort of, if God will answer our
prayers and the famine will cease,
God will not stop a season of the famine except for the
purpose of sustaining life. דכתיב *D'chtiv* as the verse says, פותח את
ידך ומשביע לכל חי רצון *potei'ach et yadecha u'masbia l'chol chai ratzon*.
When you open up your hand, you satiate all living things. So
ומשביע *u'masbia* and it's חי *chai*, it's about bringing about life. ומנלן
דלא מצלינן אתרתי *U'minalan d'lo matzli'nan a'tarti*? Now where do you get
this idea you can't pray for two things? דכתיב *D'chtiv* because the
verse says, ונצומה ונבקשה מאלהינו על זאת *v'natzuma v'nivakshah m'elokeinu al zot*.
Let us fast and ask from our God on this, this one
thing. מכלל דאיכא אחריתי *Michlal d'ika achriti*. You see there's another thing,
but we're only going to ask for one. So presumably you're only
supposed to focus on one thing. By the way, notice in the
פסוק *pasuk* the linking of fasting and prayer. ונצומה ונבקשה *V'natzuma v'nivakshah*,
which is again so central to this מסכת *masechet*. Okay, מכלל דאיכא
אחריתי *michlal d'ika achriti*. וממערבא אמרי משמיה דרבי חגי מהא *U'mimarav amri
mishmei d'Rabbi Chagai me'ha*. לרחמין למבעא מן קדם אלה שמיא על רזא
דנה *L'rachamin l'mib'ei min kodam elah shamaya al raza denah* and compassion
to ask from the God of heaven on this matter. מכלל דאיכא
אחריתי *Michlal d'ika achriti* which implies that there's another thing, but we're
only asking about this. בימי רבי זירא גזר גזירה *Be'mei Rabbi Zeira
gezar gzeira*. Now in the time of רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira* there
was an edict from the government, and opposed to other edicts such
as not to keep שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* and not to do ברית
מילה *bris milah*, here was the edict: דגזר דלא למיתב בתעניתא *d'gozar
d'lo l'mitav b'ta'anita*. The גזירה *gezeira* was you cannot have a public
religious fast. So that's interesting. And presumably there was a famine and
there was a drought and they needed to fast. So אמר להו
רבי זירא *amlei Rabbi Zeira* so רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira* said to
the people: נקבלינהו עלן *nikablun aleivan*. Let's accept on ourselves the obligation
to
fast, ולכי בטלה הגזירה *u'l'chi batla hagezeira*, and when the גזירה *gezeira*
passes, ליתביה *leisvei* then we'll fulfill our vow,
we'll obligate ourselves to fast and we'll fulfill it when we have
the opportunity.
What's the verb for למיתב בתעניתא *l'meitav b'ta'anita*? What does it mean?
To sit. Right. למיתב *L'meitav* means to sit in a fast. Right.
So we don't know that they're praying, do we?
No. So now we have shifted from prayer to fast. The פסוק
*pasuk* before was like a hint, ונצומה ונבקשה *v'natzuma v'nivakshah*, right? So
until now it's all been about prayer of מסכת תענית ta'anit *Masechet
Ta'anit*. All the discussion's been about prayer. Now we're finally dealing with
fasting as somewhat of a parallel or of an equivalent, of an
equivalent.
It's a non-verbal mode of prayer. It's exactly what it seems to
be, as opposed to we tend to focus on fasting as a
type of תשובה *teshuvah*. Here it is not about תשובה *teshuvah*. It's
all about prayer. And fasting, I think that said extremely well, is
a type of non-verbal prayer. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, אמר ליה
מנלן לך הא *amlei minalan lach ha*, where do you get this
idea that just making an acceptance of an obligation to fast also
is efficacious even if you're not able to fast? So אמר ליה
דכתיב *amlei d'chtiv* because the פסוק *pasuk* says, vayomer elai, God said
to me, by דניאל *Daniel*, אל תירא דניאל כי מן היום הראשון
אשר נתת לבך להבין ולהתענות לפני אלהיך נשמעו דבריך *al tira Daniel
ki min hayom harishon asher natata libcha l'havin u'l'hitanot lifnei elokecha nishma'u
devarecha*. Oh, so good to read דניאל *Daniel* as opposed to איוב
*Iyov*. At least these פסוקים *pesukim* of
דניאל *Daniel* are not as easy. Anyway, from the very day that
you have placed your heart in order to understand and to fast
before your God, your words have been heard. So נתת לבך *natata
libcha*, not from the day you have fasted, from the day you
intended to fast, your words have been heard. Okay, but again notice
the connection of התענות *hit'anot* and נשמעו דבריך *nishma'u devarecha*, fast and
hearing of the prayers. Okay, but again though your idea of a
non-verbal prayer, making a commitment is not necessarily a non-verbal prayer, but
to some degree it's also seen, I would say, as an intensifier
of the prayer. It's like we're crying out so much, it's like
you want to shake and rend your garments and you're fasting like
you're throwing your whole soul into this outreaching to God. So it's
not, I would say it's an intensifier of the prayer as well.
So to some degree even the desire to fast and that essence
of self-sacrifice
itself has that power of intensifying the prayer.
That is the association between prayer and fasting, and you have to
take seriously the words תענית *ta'anit*.
So right, so thank you. So that is exactly we're going to
see in the later משניות because it speaks that they were גוזר
תענית gozer ta'anit and then the next משנה mishna says ולא נענו.
v'lo na'anu ולא נענו na'anu
and they were not answered. So תענית and ענה anah is absolutely
and think about one of the earliest prayers that we have, which
we're going to read in a משנה is the עננו Anenu prayer.
Right, כעננו כמו שענית כמו שענית k'anenu kmo she'anita kmo she'anita so
ענה anah and נענו and תענית are you absolutely. All right,
let's just see one more thing. Now we switch gears a little
bit and all
of this is how important rain is and now there's an amazing
shifting of gears which is about when rain is a pain in
the neck. So let's take a look. אמר רב יצחק Amar Rav
Yitzchak אפילו שנים כשני אליהו afilu shanim k'shnei Eliyahu even if the
years were like the years of אליהו Eliyahu where there was, you
know, famine and drought for many years ירדו גשמים בערבי שבתות yardu
geshamim b'arvei shabatot but if rain comes on a Friday on a
Friday אינם אלא סימן קללה einam ela siman klala it's going to
still be a sign of curse because it gets in the way
of you being able to take care of your שבת preparations. So
היינו דאמר רבה בר שילא hainu d'amar Rabba bar Shila קשיא יומא
דמיטרא כיומא דדינא kashya yoma d'mitra k'yoma d'dina
a day of rain can sometimes be or is as difficult as
a day of דין. What does this mean? So רש"י says it
means Tuesdays and Thursdays which are Mondays and Thursdays which is when
the בתי דין batei din are and the market days and they're
so busy and tumultuous and you know so rain can sometimes you
know make, if it's pouring rain out like it is right now,
you know it might be good for the crops but it makes
your life a little bit hard on sometimes. Now I do want
to say something and with this we'll end which is, okay, so
on the one hand this was like it's a little like it's
jarring, let's say the power and importance of rain, נבך nebach so
you're going to have a Friday that you're going to be hard
to go to the marketplace but you know the crops need the
rain right? It's like a little hard to understand but I think
that the key here is not קללה klala but סימן קללה siman
klala because again the question is how is God communicating to us
through the rain. So the rain itself might be a ברכה bracha
might be needed for the crops but the fact that it's God
is bringing it at this difficult time is a סימן קללה siman
klala right? It's still showing a certain degree of disfavor. So I
think that that's important. Not like he's saying it's objectively a bad
thing, it might objectively be a very good and a necessary thing,
but it's still it's still God sending us a message, a bad
message. Why is it being brought now when it makes it difficult
rather than at a time when it would be less difficult? And
again so I think rather than just complaining over trivial things, it's
important in terms of the theological point of trying to say what
message are we being sent and what are we being told, you
know through the rain.